Charles Sheldon papers, 1912-1922
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Charles Sheldon collection, 1912-1922
AZ 408
Sheldon, Charles, 1867-1928
This collection consists chiefly of two journals and photographic materials documenting Charles Sheldon's desert bighorn sheep collecting expeditions from 1912 to 1916. The second journal also documents his studies of the Seri Indians and Tiburon Island, 1921-1922.
.75 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None.
Biographical Note
Hunter, naturalist, and conservationist Charles Sheldon (1867-1928) collected, photographed, and observed wildlife. From 1903 to 1908 he devoted his time to the study of wildlife in the northwestern part of the North American continent, hunting grizzly bears in the upper Yukon and Denali. From 1912 to 1922, he shifted his focus to the Southwest, hunting and collecting desert bighorn sheep from Arizona to Sonora, Mexico. Sheldon was a key figure in both the development of the Mount McKinley National Park in Alaska, and the establishment of the National Wildlife Refuge System. Hundreds of the biological specimens that Sheldon collected are now in the National Museum at the Smithsonian. For further biographical information, see The Wilderness of the Southwest.
Organization
This collection is organized into two series:
I. Journals, 1912-1922
II. Photographs, 1912-1916
Scope and Content Note
This collection consists chiefly of two journals and photographic materials documenting Charles Sheldon's desert bighorn sheep collecting expeditions from 1912 to 1916. The second journal also documents his studies of the Seri Indians and Tiburon Island, 1921-1922.
Access Terms
Sheldon, Charles, 1867-1928 -- Diaries
Bighorn sheep hunting -- Arizona
Bighorn sheep hunting -- Mexico -- Sonora (State)
Seri Indians -- Social life and customs
Hunters -- Diaries
Sonora (Mexico: State) -- Description and travel
Journals
Photographs
Notes
Related Material
Books relating to Sheldon's research include: The Wilderness of Desert Bighorns and Seri Indians, and The Wilderness of the Southwest.
Container List
- Series I: Journals, 1912-1922
  Journals and notes regarding expeditions to Arizona and Sonora, Mexico, to collect and study desert bighorn sheep, 1921-1916. Includes observations of the wildlife and Seri Indians in the Sierra Seri and Tiburon Island, 1921-1922.
  - Desert bighorn sheep expeditions; Grand Canyon, hunting sheep with Havasupai Indians; The Arizona-Sonora border; Pinacate region, Sonora, Mexico; and Sierra Del Rosario, Sonora. 1912-1916 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Seri Indians and Tiburon Island. 1921-1922 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Series II: Photographs, 1912-1916
  Consists of black and white photographs of Sheldon's 1912-1916 desert bighorn sheep collecting expeditions. Included are photographs of the Grand Canyon hunting excursion and the Havasupai Indians who accompanied Sheldon. Among the Arizona-Sonora photographs are images of the Tinajas, Tuseral, and Gila Mountains; pioneer gravesites; a saguaro girdled by grazing bighorn sheep; and specimens of desert bighorn sheep. The Pinacate region photographs include Pinacate Peak and surrounding lava fields; MacDougal Crater; a bighorn hunt at MacDougal Pass; and flowers near Hornaday Mountain. The Sierra Del Rosario photographs include the El Rosario Ram and the Del Rosario Mountains.
  - Grand Canyon, hunting sheep with Havasupai Indians. 1912 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - The Arizona-Sonora border. 1913 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Pinacate region, Sonora, Mexico. 1915 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Sierra Del Rosario, Sonora. 1916 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous, with negatives. 1912-1916 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous, no negatives. 1912-1916 (Box 2, Folder 6)